Colm, Gerhard; Records ger029
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Gerhard Colm Papers
1929-1972
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger029
2.0 cubic ft.
Gerhard Colm was a professor of economics at the New School for Social Research and an expert on public revenues, unemployment, and economic planning. He served as the Chief Economist of the National Planning Association and as a leading economic adviser for both the Roosevelt and Truman administrations.
Biographical Sketch
Gerhard Colm was best known for his work as the Chief Economist of the National Planning Association and serving as a leading economic adviser for both the Roosevelt and Truman administrations.
Gerhard Colm was born on June 30, 1897 in Hannover, Germany to Emil and Olga Strassburger Colm. He received his doctorate in 1921 from the University of Freiburg and did post-graduate work at the University of Munich and the University of Berlin (1921-1922). Colm served as a statistician for the German government from 1921-1927, but left government service to enter academia as head of the research division of the Institute of World Economics at the University of Kiel from 1927-1933.
Colm's active participation in groups agitating against the Freikorps and other pro-Hitler organizations forced him to emigrate in 1933 to the United States as a refugee from Nazi Germany. Colm came to New York as one of the founding members of the University in Exile of the New School for Social Research, to which he was elected Dean of Exiled Scholars in 1938.
In 1939 Colm was named by Secretary of Commerce Harry L. Hopkins as Fiscal and Financial expert of the new industrial economics division of that department. In this capacity Colm developed national income estimates for economic planning. One year later Colm became principal fiscal analyst of the Bureau of the Budget and assistant chief of the division, a position he held until 1946. In addition, Colm lectured at George Washington University from 1940-1962 and served the U.S. government on many special economic missions to foreign countries. From 1946 to 1952 he was economist on the Council of Economic Advisors, Executive Office of the President. In 1952 Colm joined the private sector as Chief Economist for the National Planning Association, remaining in that position until his death. He died on December 26, 1968 in Chevy Chase, Maryland.
Colm was married twice, first to Hanna Nicolassen on September 11, 1922 until her death on March 21, 1965. They had four children, Peter, Ann, Stine and Claus. Colm married his second wife, Mascha Gilde on April 11, 1966.
1897 Born in Hamburg, Germany on June 30 to Emil and Olga (Strassburger) Colm
1920 Student at the University of Munich
1921 Received Ph.D. in Political Science from the University of Freiburg
1921-1923 Advanced study at the University of Berlin
1921-1927 Economist with the Federal Statistical Bureau, Berlin, Germany
1922 Married on September 11 to Hanna Nicolassen
1927-1933 Instructor and then Professor of Economics at the University of Kiel, Institute of World Economics
1933 Emigrated to the United States with wife, Hanna Colm
1938 Publication with Fritz Lehmann of Economic Consequences of Recent American Tax Policy
1933-1939 Professor of Economics at the New School for Social Research
1939 Became naturalized U.S. citizen
1939-1940 Fiscal expert for the Department of Commerce, Washington, D.C.
1940 Co-author with Helen Tarasov of Who pays the Taxes?
1940-1962 Professorial lecturer at George Washington University
1940-1946 Chief fiscal analyst, Bureau of the Budget, Washington, D.C.
1946 Member of the Special mission of the American Military Government to Germany for preparation plan of financial reform
1946-1952 Economist on the Council of Economic Advisers, Executive Office of the President
1952 Co-authored with Marilyn Young American Economy in 1960
1952-1968 Chief Economist of the National Planning Association
1955 Co-authored with Helen O. Nicol Essays in Public Finance and Fiscal Policy
1958 Co-authored with Theodor Gieger The Economy of the American People
1961 Received honorary doctorate from the University of Frankfurt
1964 Received honorary doctorate from the New School for Social Research, New York; recipient of the Bernard Harms Prize from the Institute of World Economists
1965 Death of wife, Hanna, on March 21 in Fairfax, Virginia
1966 Second marriage to Mascha Gilde on April 11
1968 Died on December 25 in Chevy Chase, Maryland, survived by his widow Mascha Colm and four children, Peter, Anne, Stine and Claus
Scope and Contents
The Gerhard Colm Papers, 1929-1972, (2 cu. ft.) have been divided into seven series: 1) Biographical materials; 2) Correspondence of Gerhard Colm, 1929-1967; 3) Hans Staudinger Correspondence,1969-1972; 4) Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm, 1930-1967; 5) Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under his supervision) for the National Planning Association, 1952-1968; 6) Manuscripts by others; and 7) Miscellaneous materials.
The bulk of the collection consists of Colm's writings, both private publications (1930-1967) as well as those published under the auspices of the National Planning Association (1952-1968). Included in his writings for the National Planning Association are a number of pamphlets, his economic projections for the coming years, as well as his addresses to House and Senate Subcommittees on various fiscal matters. The collection contains only a small amount of correspondence to and from Colm (including Hans Staudinger), but also contains Staudinger's correspondence after Colm's death with various contemporaries to establish the Gerhard Colm Memorial Lecture Series at the New School for Social Research.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Biographical materials
Series 2: Correspondence of Gerhard Colm, 1929-1967
Series 3: Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerning the Gerhard Colm Memorial Lecture series, 1969-1972
Series 4: Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm, 1930-1967
Series 5: Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under his supervision) for the National Planning Association, 1952-1968
Series 6: Manuscripts by others, mostly undated
Series 7: Miscellaneous materials
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Mrs. Mascha Colm in November 1982; other items pertaining to Prof. Colm were added to the collection from the Hans Staudinger Papers.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Economics; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees.; Public welfare.; Economics -- Study and teaching.; Colm, Gerhard, 1897-1968.; Staudinger, Hans, 1889-1980.; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997); National Planning Association.
- Biographical materials, 1968-1970; Undated; 1; 7 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists primarily of materials concerning the establishment of The Gerhard Colm Memorial Lecture Series at the New School for Social Research, 1969-1970. Also in this series are memorial addresses and obituaries after the death of Colm.
  - Obituaries, memorials, 1968-1969 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 1)
  - Biographical questionnaire, lexicon entries, clippings, 1965-1976 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 2)
  - Gerhard Colm Memorial Lectures. General information, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 3)
  - Gerhard Colm Memorial Lectures. Hans Staudinger notes, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 4)
  - First Gerhard Colm Memorial Lecture, 1970 March 20 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 5)
    Walter W. Heller. "Excerpts from 'Economics of the Race Problem'".
  - First Gerhard Colm Memorial Lecture: Samuel Bowles: Discussant, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 6)
  - First Gerhard Colm Memorial Lecture: Robert S. Browne: Discussant, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 7)
- Correspondence of Gerhard Colm, 1929-1967; 2; 9 file folders
  This series contains a small amount of correspondence of Colm, including correspondence with Hans Staudinger of the New School for Social Research.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Board of Governors, Federal Reserve System, 1936 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence of Gerhard Colm), Folder 8)
  - Fachgemeinschaften und Ausschüsse des Bundes Deutscher Frauenvereine, 1929 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence of Gerhard Colm), Folder 9)
  - Foreman, Clark, 1936 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence of Gerhard Colm), Folder 10)
  - Heimann, Eduard, 1947 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence of Gerhard Colm), Folder 11)
  - The Journal of Political Economy, 1937-1938 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence of Gerhard Colm), Folder 12)
  - Mills, Wilbur D. (The National Planning Association), 1967 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence of Gerhard Colm), Folder 13)
  - Richter-Altschäffer, Hans, 1938 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence of Gerhard Colm), Folder 14)
  - Staudinger, Hans, 1957-1966 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence of Gerhard Colm), Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936; 1953; 1957 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence of Gerhard Colm), Folder 16)
- Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerning the Gerhard Colm Memorial Lecture series, 1969-1972; 3; 24 file folders
  This series contains correspondence between Hans Staudinger and others in reference to the Colm lecture series, in particular with Mascha Colm and Walter Heller.
  - Altschul, Frank, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 17)
  - Bamberg, H. George, 1970-1972 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 18)
  - Bernstein, Peter, 1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 19)
  - Bowles, Samuel, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 20)
  - Brimmer, Andrew F., 1969-1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 21)
  - Browne, Robert S., 1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 22)
  - Buchenholz, Jane J., 1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 23)
  - Colm, Mascha, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 24)
  - Cranford, Victoria, 1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 25)
  - Deyrup, Felicia, 1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 26)
  - Ehrlich, Edna, 1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 27)
  - Greenbaum, Joseph J., 1969-1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 28)
  - Heilbronner, Robert, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 29)
  - Heller, Walter H., 1969-1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 30)
  - Lowe, Adolph, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 31)
  - National Planning Association (John Miller), 1969-1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 32)
  - Pfleiderer, Otto, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 33)
  - Roper, Elmo, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 34)
  - Schaffner, Joe, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 35)
  - Sonenblum, Sidney, 1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 36)
  - Sonne, H. Christian, 1969-1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 37)
  - Tobin, James, 1969 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 38)
  - Vietorisz, Thomas, 1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 39)
  - Wallich, Henry C., 1970 (Box 1 (3-Hans Staudinger Correspondence, primarily concerni), Folder 40)
- Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm, 1930-1967; 4; 56 file folders
  This series contains primarily reprints of articles published by Cohn in scholarly journals, as well as several original typescripts and mimeographed speech texts.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Der Mensch im Wirtschaftlichen Kreislauf. Tübingen: J.C.B. Mohr (Paul Siebeck), 1930 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 41)
  - Wege auf der Weltkrise. Excerpts, Undated (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 42)
  - Essays in Public Finance and Fiscal Policy. New York: Oxford University Press, 1955 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 43)
  - "Über den Inhalt und den Erkenntniswert der Zahlungsbilanz", Undated; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 44)
  - "Democracy and Arbitration of Industrial Disputes", Undated; typescript (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 45)
  - "Is Economic Planning Compatible with Democracy?", Undated; typescript (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 46)
  - Review of Arnd Jessen, Der vollkommene Haushaltsplan. Ein Beitrag zur Theorie der Haushaltsform, 1929; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 47)
  - Review of Staatseinnahmen aus Steuern und Zöllen im Deutschen Reich und im Auslande, 1930; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 48)
  - "Wege aus der Weltwirtschaftskrise", 1931 November; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 49)
  - "Deutschland und die Weltkrise", 1932; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 50)
  - Review of Öffentliche Hand und Wirtschaftsgestaltung, 1932 July; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 51)
  - "Zahlungsbilanz", 1933; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 52)
  - "Politique commerciale allemande", 1933 May; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 53)
  - "Theory of Public Expenditures"The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Vol. 183, 1-11, 1936 January (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 54)
  - "Public Spending and Recovery in the United States", 1936 May; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 55)
  - "Public Revenue and Public Expenditure in the National Income" reprints. Text of paper, 1936 December 29 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 56)
  - Review of Hans Richter-Altschäffer Volkswirtschaftliche Theorie der öffentlichen Investitionen. Reprints, 1937 December (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 57)
  - "The Revenue Act of 1938", 1938 September; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 58)
  - "Tax Policy and Capital Formation", 1939 February; reprint of paper (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 59)
  - "Gerhard Colm Discusses the Basis of Federal Fiscal Policy". Reprints, 1939 June (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 60)
  - "Who pays the taxes?", 1940; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 61)
  - "Comments on I. W. King: 'Are We Suffering from Economic Maturity?'", 1940 February; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 62)
  - "How to Finance Defense". Text of paper, 1941 March 4 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 63)
  - "Round Table Discussion -- Who Pays the Taxes?" Text of discussion, 1942 June 10 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 64)
  - "On the Road to Economic Stabilization", 1948 September; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 65)
  - "Why Public Finance?", 1948 September; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 66)
  - "Experiences in the Use of Social Accounting in Public Policy in the United States". Text of conference paper, Cambridge, England, 1949 August 27-1949 September 3 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 67)
  - "A Plan for the Liquidation of War Finance and the Financial Rehabilitation of Germany", ca. 1950; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 68)
  - "'Don't Throw the Baby Out With the Bath'. Comments on recent articles on Progressive Income and Corporate Income Taxes", 1953; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 69)
  - "Entwicklungen in Konjunkturforschung und Konjunkturpolitik in den Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika", 1954; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 70)
  - "Economic Analysis for a Time of Change". Abstract of a paper, 1954 May 24 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 71)
  - "Die Selbstverpflichtung des amerikanischen Volkes zur Vollbeschäftigungs-politik", 1956; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 72)
  - "Economic Implications of Disarmament". Reprints, 1957 July (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 73)
  - "Wirtschaftsverfassung, Finanzwirtschaft und Finanzwissenschaft", 1959; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 74)
  - "Financial Needs and Resources over the Next Decade at All Levels of Government", 1959 April 10-11; typescript (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 75)
  - "Observations of a Foreign Visitor on the Japanese Economic Development", 1960 May; typescript (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 76)
  - "In Defense of the Public Interest", 1960 Autumn; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 77)
  - "Amerikanische Konjunkturpolitik am Scheideweg", 1961 July 28; typescript of speech (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 78)
  - "A National Economic Budget"The New Republic, No. 16, 34-39, 1962 October 20 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 79)
  - "Discussion", 1963; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 80)
  - "The Economics of the Current Fiscal Policy Proposals in the United States", 1963 September; mimeographed typescript (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 81)
  - "Economic Planning in the United States", 1964; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 82)
  - "Weltwirtschaftliche Forschung im Zeitalter der Koexistenz", 1964; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 83)
  - "Economic Prospects", 1964 March 20; mimeographed typescript (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 84)
  - "Projecting Federal Revenues and Expenditures". Reprints, 1965 June (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 85)
  - "On Goals Research", 1965 June 28; typescript (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 86)
  - "National Goals Analysis and Marginal Utility Economics", 1965 July; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 87)
  - "Projecting Federal Revenues and Expenditures. Highlights of Federal Budget Projections. A New Study by Gerhard Colm and Peter Wagner", 1965 Fall; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 88)
  - "On Goals Research", 1966 April; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 89)
  - Review of Andrew Shonfield Modern Capitalism. The Changing Balance of Public and Private Power, 1966 August 23; typescript (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 90)
  - "The Role and Impact of Government R & D Information", 1966 December 2; typescript, photocopy (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 91)
  - "Comments on the proposed Full Opportunity and Social Accounting Act of 1967". Seminar paper prepared for the Subcommittee on Government Research, Senate Committee on Government Operations, 1967 June 26 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 92)
  - "Letter to Gert von Eynern", 1967 July 4; typescript, reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 93)
  - "On the Problems of Program Appraisal in the Field of Development of Human Resources". Paper, 1967 November 28 (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 94)
  - "The Planning-Programming-Budgeting System", 1967 December; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 95)
  - "Concluding Comments", Undated; reprint (Box 1 (4-Writings and publications of Gerhard Colm), Folder 96)
- Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under his supervision) for the National Planning Association, 1952-1968; 5; 47 file folders
  This series contains pamphlets and mimeographed typescripts of essays published under the auspices of the National Planning Association, either authored by, co-authored by or prepared under the supervision of Gerhard Colm, Director of the National Planning Association.
  - The American Economy in 1960. Economic Progress in a World of Tension. Planning Pamphlets, No. 81, 1952 December (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 1)
  - Can We Afford Additional Programs for National Security? Planning Pamphlets, No. 84, 1953 October (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 2)
  - "The Economic Outlook for 1954", 1954 January (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 3)
  - Opportunities for Economic Expansion. Planning Pamphlets, No. 87, 1954 July (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 4)
    also preliminary draft.
  - "The Economic Outlook for 1955", 1955 January (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 5)
  - "The Economic Outlook for 1956", 1955 December (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 6)
  - "Summary of Testimony on Budget Policy and Economic Growth Presented to. the Subcommittee on Tax Policy and the Joint Committee on the Economic Report, December 5, 1955", 1955 December 5; mimeographed typescript (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 7)
  - The Employment Act Past and Future. A Tenth Anniversary Symposium. National Planning Association, Special Report No. 41, 1956 February (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 8)
  - "The Economic Outlook for 1957", 1956 December (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 9)
  - "Statement of Gerhard Colm before the Subcommittee on Disarmament of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee", 1957 March 7; mimeographed typescript (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 10)
  - "General Economic Feasibility of National Security Programs", 1957 March 20; mimeographed typescript of paper (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 11)
  - "Statement of Dr. Gerhard Colm, National Planning Association". Text of House of Representatives Subcommittee hearings, 1957 April 5 (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 12)
  - "Statement of Gerhard Colm before the Subcommittee on Fiscal Policy of the Joint Economic Committee", 1957 June 4; mimeographed typescript (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 13)
  - "The Economic Outlook for 1958", 1957 December (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 14)
  - The Economy of the American People. Progress, Problems, Prospects. Planning Pamphlet No. 102, 1958 March (Box 2 (5-Publications and papers prepared by Colm (or under), Folder 15)
    also preliminary draft; reprint of summary version.